<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration and proclamation of the Deputy-General of Ireland, concerning the present hand of God in the visitation of the plague; and for the exercise of fasting and prayer in relation thereunto.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1650 : Ireton)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E612_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206477</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865633</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87204)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E612[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration and proclamation of the Deputy-General of Ireland, concerning the present hand of God in the visitation of the plague; and for the exercise of fasting and prayer in relation thereunto.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1650 : Ireton)</author>
                  <author>Ireton, Henry, 1611-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Cork in the Year of our Lord, 1650. Reprinted at London by John Field,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plague --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117881:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION AND PROLCAMATION OF The Deputy-General of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Concerning The preſent hand of God in the Viſitation OF THE PLAGUE; And for the Exerciſe of Faſting and Prayer in relation thereunto.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Cork</hi> in the Year of our Lord, 1650.</p>
            <p>Reprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>John Field.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117881:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117881:2"/>
            <head>IRELAND,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſed the Lord our God, now a long while to ſtretch forth his heavy hand over this Nation in general, and the Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in thoſe capital Judgements of the Sword and Peſtilence (with ſomewhat of Famine alſo in many places;) and eſpecially by that Plague of Peſtilence (as with his <hi>own</hi> more <hi>immediate hand</hi>) to ſweep away, in a maner, whole Towns and Cities, and lay waſte almoſt whole Countreys, and to ſpread the contagion throughout into all parts (as ſadly is to be ſeen at this day) And that eminent hand of his (which <hi>of late</hi> was ſo heavy onely, or <hi>chiefly,</hi> upon <hi>the Enemies</hi> of his and his Peoples Cauſe, and upon others the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Land, with <hi>diſtinguiſhing Mercy,</hi> and forbearance towards thoſe his poor creatures that ſerve him in that Cauſe) hath of late been extended to the taking away of many of them alſo, and not Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers onely, but many Officers (and more of them, in proportion, then of the other) as alſo many other <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant people,</hi> both of the ancient Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and ſuch as have more lately come over to us; and of all theſe, not onely the common ſort, but many even of thoſe that have more eminently profeſſed his fear, and divers ſuch as we have cauſe to eſteem his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117881:3"/>own people, dear and precious in his ſight, ſo as that former diſcriminating Mercy of his, ſeems now to be turned into <hi>a general diſpleaſure,</hi> and univerſal Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And his deſtroying Angel (ſtriking here and there round about us) ſeems to come near to us, to the Doors, and even into the Houſes or Tents of us that yet ſurvive, even of thoſe that are eſteemed <hi>beſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. And thus thoſe, whom he hath ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully preſerved and provided for in times and places of greateſt hazard and ſcarcity, and owned both here and in <hi>England,</hi> in doing great things for them and by them, as yet he ceaſeth not to do (<hi>which I deſire we and all his people may ever acknowledge to his praiſe,</hi> and that his and our Enemies might to their convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) Though he yet delivers them not over into the hands of men, but rather makes them ſtill more and more Maſters over their Enemies, and thoſe that hate them, yet (as in ſome other kindes both of Diſeaſes and Hardſhips, wherewith he hath formerly afflicted us, ſo in this now) he is pleaſed <hi>to chaſtiſe</hi> with his own hand, and taking away many (whether in Judgement for their own and our ſins or unworthineſs, or in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as from the evil to come) doth every way threaten and warn thoſe of us that remain, and <hi>calls upon all men every where to repent,</hi> and not to think that thoſe he hath thought fitteſt to take away, <hi>were greater ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners then our ſelves,</hi> but all of us to <hi>ſearch our hearts, and try our ways, and turn unto himſelf, that he may heal us, and have mercy upon us.</hi> Now though none of the <hi>works</hi> of our God are without their grounds or ends, or without <hi>their ſpeakings and teachings</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Sons of men, and eſpecially to thoſe whom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117881:3"/>he hath given eyes to ſee: And though in theſe caſes of Judgements, no men (no not the moſt ſanctified amongſt us) need to ſeek far for cauſes more then ſufficient of his juſt diſpleaſure againſt them (further then Mercy through our Mediator Chriſt Jeſus, and Faith in given him, turns it into Free-grace and favor) yet ſuch <hi>extraordinary diſpenſations, being not without their extraordinary grounds and ends,</hi> It is the duty of all, and muſt needs be the deſire and practice of the Faithful (through the grace and wiſdom given them) to ſearch in themſelves, and humbly to ſeek from the Lord, that they may underſtand what thoſe are, that in ſuch dealings of his <hi>he would have them eſpecially take notice of.</hi> And though ſuch as have intereſt in the ſure and everlaſting Covenant of Mercy, need not, and ſo (ſo far as it is ſealed unto them) they do not or ought not fear that God hath, or ever will break that Covenant, or take away thoſe everlaſting Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of his in Chriſt Jeſus towards them, yet even ſuch (conſidering how they through the fleſh do unworthily abuſe that Mercy, and all the gracious fruits thereof, and do many other ways provoke him) ought more then others (as <hi>kindely children</hi> toward <hi>ſuch a Father</hi>) to be jealous of his juſt diſpleaſure, and tenderly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of, and affected with any ſignifications thereof, and moſt ſollicitouſly to ſearch and ſeek out (that they may be <hi>kindely humbled for,</hi> and <hi>in future avoid) the occaſions</hi> thereof in themſelves: And conſidering that in thoſe things which concern our Temporary being, and the comfort or diſcomfort thereof (wherein he hath foretold he would correct even the ſeed of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> (his choſen and anointed one) when they offend,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117881:4"/>
               <hi>notwithſtanding his ſure Covenant for everlaſting mercies,</hi> which he would not break or take away) <hi>He doth not vainly afflict nor grieve the children of men;</hi> and then eſpecially not thoſe he hath adopted for his own, but does it <hi>for ſome ends</hi> of good towards them (as for <hi>reproving, or reſtraining, for awakening, or quickning, for humbling, teaching or inſtructing, for purging or purifying, for trying or perfecting of them, &amp;c.</hi> as he findes <hi>they need</hi>) and of glory to himſelf in and from them, they ought not to be regardleſs and unſenſible of, but carefully to obſerve each motion of his hand, and <hi>pointing</hi> of his finger, and to watch, ſtudy, and humbly to ſeek, that they may finde out his minde and meaning in all, and eſpecially in ſuch <hi>ſignal diſpenſations</hi> of his towards them, as theſe are, and may obtain the fruit to themſelves, and render to him the glory he intends them for.</p>
            <p>Having therefore (upon the aforeſaid <hi>eminent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> given to my ſelf and others in this Nation) ſome ſenſe and conſideration (through Grace) in my own heart concerning theſe things, and much more then I have the time or faculty to bring forth in ſuitable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, I thought good to commend the ſame to others, and provoke them to a further ſenſe and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of them, and to a <hi>diligent practice ſuitable thereunto,</hi> leaving and recommending them to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther improved and <hi>heightned,</hi> both in my ſelf and others, through the working of the ſame Spirit of Grace in Chriſt Jeſus, by which alone, any ſuch ſenſe is wrought in me: And conſidering, that as the people of God ought to be ſenſible of, and duly affected with all the Judgements of God in the world (even againſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117881:4"/>wicked men, and their enemies, ſo as to give glory to God in them <hi>(which worldly men themſelves will not)</hi> to pray and intercede for Mercy and forbearance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them (ſo far as may ſtand with his honor and good pleaſure) and to be humbled under the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their own equal unworthineſs and ill-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (further then as infinite Mercy paſſeth by, or Grace makes a difference) and to take warning, and be bettered in themſelves by ſuch examples) ſo much more ought they, many other ways, to be affected, when they ſee God ſmite their fellows (thoſe that are dear to him as themſelves) and ſo, or otherwiſe, ſtriking at or near themſelves (which ſhould, amongſt other effects, awaken and ſtir us up to conſider what, and how great thoſe evils muſt be, that ſo provoke or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage God to ſeem (as it were, for the time) to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the glory of his Mercy and Truth, to thoſe that profeſs and truſt his Name, for the <hi>neceſſary vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his Juſtice, and greater glory of his Mercy at the laſt) And that when his mighty hand is ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently lifted up, as he expects and requires all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men ſhould be humbled under it, and his own eſpecially; ſo it becomes thoſe that are ſo indeed, to expreſs and declare it, both before Him, and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Men, in all the ways he hath required or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his acceptance of, and to take ſhame to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and witneſs to his Righteous Judgements, and implore his mercy and forbearance; I do therefore commend unto all that have any thing of <hi>true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> in them, within this Dominion, the frequent exerciſe of Prayer with Faſting <hi>(ſuch as is without Superſtition)</hi> and (ſuitable to the Faith, Simplicity,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117881:5"/>Truth and Purity of the Goſpel) during the time of this our Calamity, with humble Acknowledgements and Confeſſions before God (to our ſhame and his glory) and fervent Interceſſions (as the Spirit of Chriſt ſhall enable) in behalf of the many places and people of this Land, now ſo ſadly viſited and afflicted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; eſpecially of <hi>Dublin, Wexford, Roſs, Kilkenny, Carrick, Clonmel</hi> and <hi>Youghall,</hi> and the ſeveral parts of the Army throughout our Quarters, in Gariſon or Field, eſpecially in <hi>Leinſter</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> That God would ſtay that his afflicting hand, and ſpare his poor people (<hi>eſpecially thoſe that ſerve and truly ſeek him</hi> in this Countrey and Cauſe) that he would ſhew us wherein we have eſpecially offended, or do diſpleaſe him; what his minde and meaning is towards us; what he would have us learn by theſe his loud and dreadful ſpeakings, and (eſpecially) what our carriage and dealings <hi>ſhould have been,</hi> and what he would have it be, towards the <hi>generality</hi> of the people, and our Enemies here, whether in reſpect of <hi>Juſtice (for inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Blood)</hi> or of more <hi>moderation</hi> and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any; and that he would guide us in his way, to do according to his own minde therein; bow and bend our hearts to conform unto, and faithfully to follow and purſue what he ſhall teach us to be <hi>his minde and will in all things;</hi> and <hi>give out a true Spirit</hi> of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation for, and univerſal Reformation of thoſe many evils that abound amongſt us, and a faithful zeal for it (eſpecially in us the Officers towards thoſe under our charge) and this as in reſpect of all evils, ſo eſpecially of thoſe that are moſt crying and prevailing (as Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Blaſpheming, Drunkenneſs, Plundring, Exaction
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117881:5"/>and Cruelty towards people in protection (where any opportunity with hope of privacy is found) curſed Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, and <hi>Self-ſeeking</hi> in general (the root of many other Evils) and neglect of God, his ways and worſhip) that he would every way <hi>enlarge his Spirit</hi> upon his poor Servants here, and advance the truth and <hi>power of Godlineſs more</hi> amongſt us, make us a people fit for him to own, uſe and bleſs yet further in his Work, for good in the world, and not onely to deſtroy, and be deſtroyed; and would ſo take off his afflicting hand from us, and reſtore health and ſafety to us, and ſoundneſs within our Tents and Dwellings, and turn our <hi>now required Mourning</hi> into Praiſes; and alſo in behalf of the <hi>poor deluded Popiſh people of this Nation</hi> (captivated and kept in miſerable darkneſs and bondage by their <hi>ſeducing Prieſts and Leaders</hi>) and, amongſt them, even for our very Enemies, that all of them (ſo far as may ſtand with the good pleaſure of God, and with the glory and <hi>Righteouſneſs of his Works and Judgements in the world</hi>) may at length be made ſenſible of the <hi>great weight</hi> of ſo much crying innocent Blood, whereof (as principals or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipants) they generally ſtand guilty; of their malice and cruelty (ſo far as they finde power and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) and of their continued abominable Treachery to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all that concur not with them in their own Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, Idolatry and affected Ignorance, or indeed that <hi>worſhip not the Beaſt</hi> as they do: And alſo of the eminent and glorious hand of God, exalted <hi>ſo conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly and conſtantly</hi> every where againſt them, for theſe and the many other Iniquities and Abominations abounding amongſt them; ſo as from Conviction
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117881:6"/>thereof, they may take ſhame and confuſion to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and <hi>their Idols,</hi> and give glory to the living God; and (if poſſible) the wrath of God may be appeaſed towards them, and <hi>not utterly deſtroy them and their Nation;</hi> and that thoſe of them who are capable of his eternal Mercies, may be truly and <hi>ſpiritually hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> under his mighty hand, taken off from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of any Self-or-Creature-confidence, and brought to ſee, and finde the pure and free mercies of God in Jeſus Chriſt; and, for that purpoſe, may have their eyes opened, and hearts enlarged to diſcern and embrace the <hi>true light</hi> and freedom of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and be converted from their carnal conceptions to a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual reception thereof, <hi>and from their vain Idols to the living God;</hi> and in order thereunto (if the Lord have any purpoſe of a Church or People to himſelf to be called out amongſt them) we may, through his Grace, be made inſtruments thereof, as well as of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing their outward man; and (however) may ſo walk towards them and amongſt them, both in word and life, as not to give them occaſion of further offence, or ſtumbling at the Goſpel we profeſs, or cauſe it to be the worſe thought or ſpoken of amongſt them.</p>
            <p>And the ſame exerciſe of Faſting and Prayer, which I thus recommend for frequent uſe to thoſe within this Nation (now more immediately concerned in the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of it) I do earneſtly deſire may be uſed for the ſame purpoſes and in the ſame behalfs (as God ſhall give freedom and opportunity) by other Chriſtians of the Reformed Religion in other places (who ſhall take notice hereof, and whoſe hearts God ſhall touch with a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117881:6"/>fellow-feeling of our condition; to whom I deſire our Judgments and our Shame may be as notorious, to the glory of God, as our Mercies and Succeſſes) and particularly <hi>by the Saints and Churches of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and thoſe eſpecially of the Army in our native Land <hi>(our Brethren by double and treble relation;)</hi> And, for thoſe within this Dominion (that all, who have intereſt at the Throne of Grace, may at once meet there with their joynt cryes) I have thought fit (in the Place I ſtand in here) to Appoint, and do hereby Appoint ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, the firſt, ſecond and third Tueſdays in the enſuing Moneth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to be kept and obſerved as times eſpecially ſet apart for <hi>Publique Humiliation</hi> with Faſting and Prayer, upon the occaſions, and for the ends and purpoſes before expreſſed: On the firſt whereof to begin the ſame at the Head-quarters or Camp, and at <hi>Clonmel, Youghal, Cork,</hi> and other Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons and places to which notice hereof ſhall come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and the ſecond and third to be obſerved both at the ſame, and all other places (as notice hereof ſhall be further ſpread:) On which days at the ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as aforeſaid reſpectively, I require all Officers (both Military and Civil, for thoſe under their reſpective Charges) carefully to ſee to it, that there be a general abſtinence, ſo far as comelineſs and neceſſity will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, from all worldly labors, bodily food, and other the outward comforts of this life (whereof our unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitableneſs and iniquities, and particularly our uſual exceſs in them, and over-valuing, or other abuſe of them, render us moſt unworthy) as alſo from all ſports and recreations; And likewiſe to take notice of, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh (by Impriſonment, or other fitting Penalties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117881:7"/>portionably to the Offences) not onely ſuch as ſhall contemptuouſly do to the contrary hereof, but alſo any ſuch as ſhall be found (from Idleneſs, or from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt or ſlighting of Religion, or <hi>of the hand of God</hi> in his preſent diſpenſations) to neglect the joyning with others in Prayer and Religious Exerciſe, to the purpoſes aforeſaid, in one place &amp; Society or other (not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Popiſh way:) And I exhort all <hi>true</hi> Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Reformed Religion, in the fear and dread of God, for the love of Jeſus Chriſt, and from the bowels of Charity, and fellow-feeling of each others Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to be <hi>ſeriouſly affectionate in this Exerciſe;</hi> and that in their Addreſſes to the Throne of Grace for the aforeſaid concernments of their own, they be mindeful alſo of the <hi>Troubles and Temptations of their Brethren,</hi> wherewith they are conflicting (though in differing kindes) in other Nations, and eſpecially in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> where (beſides many other both Iniquities and Judgements) that moſt ſad and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred evil is now more then ever to be found, and further to be feared, That <hi>Brethren,</hi> profeſſing, and in each party ſome (as there's reaſon to believe) really having the ſame Faith, and hope of the Goſpel, and the ſame Cauſe of Common Concernment (againſt the world of enemies to Chriſt, his Spirit and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that thirſt and watch to deſtroy both parties) yet (either from offence and weakneſs, or peeviſhneſs, or from worldly intereſt) not onely have been and are loaded and wounded (the one part by the other) with foul and hateful reproaches (to the diſhonor and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of the Goſpel, and the rejoycing and advantage of thoſe their Enemies) and provoked one at the other,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117881:7"/>and one of them <hi>to take the intereſt and aſsistance of the ſaid Enemies,</hi> againſt the other, and to execute (the one upon the other) that deſtruction, by thoſe Enemies deſigned againſt both; which <hi>ſad ſpectacle (moſt grievous to every true Chriſtian heart)</hi> as it calls for <hi>deepeſt</hi> Humiliation on <hi>both</hi> parts (<hi>eſpecially</hi> on that whence the cauſe hath been moſt given, or the offence with leaſt cauſe and moſt impatience taken) ſo it requires moſt earneſt Prayer and Interceſſion to our God and Father of thoſe that are faithful on either part (which I deſire accordingly in theſe our Exerciſes may be uſed) that, for the Merits and Mediation, and by the Power and Spirit of his Son Chriſt Jeſus (our Lord, Head, and eldeſt Brother, <hi>the great Reconciler</hi> and Peacemaker <hi>betwixt God and Man,</hi> and amongſt men, his Members, each with other) and from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly bowels and pity towards his weak and froward children, he would now in the extremity of time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and mercifully interpoſe and <hi>bring forth ſome expedient (when men can or will finde none)</hi> to avoid and hinder (if it be his will) <hi>this hateful and dreadful evil</hi> and miſchief; and for that purpoſe would put forth and enlarge, in all that are his children <hi>in both Nations,</hi> that ſweet Spirit of Peace and Love (as well as Righteouſneſs and Judgement) which is his Sons; to convince and reprove every one of them for their ſeveral offences and evils, that any way occaſion this or lead to it; and to overpower and work them unto <hi>a diſpoſition of giving and receiving</hi> ſatisfaction, and of bearing and forbearing towards each other (and that eſpecially in the ſtronger towards the weak) and every one (as far as they have been faulty givers, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117881:8"/>impatiently and unjuſtly takers of the offence) to take ſhame to themſelves, and give glory to God; and that ſo he would pardon the ſin, take away the offences, and <hi>heal the breaches betwixt his people,</hi> and diſcover the hypocriſie, and defeat the deſigns of thoſe his enemies (that watch the advantage for the ruine of them all, and to raiſe thereupon their own corrupt intereſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Godlineſs and Honeſty) that none that have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, may further be drawn into, or proceed in any Engagements to the deſtruction of their Brethren, the oppoſing of his <hi>Spiritual Kingdom</hi> and work in the world, or the partaking with thoſe parties and powers that are enemies thereunto: But (if it be his good pleaſure, and he ſee it conducing to the glory of his work at laſt, That there ſhould be any ſuch Engagement, even to Blood and further War) That then (pardoning the weakneſſes and failings) he would ſtill witneſs to the integrity and ſimplicity of thoſe his poor Servants in this ſame <hi>old Cauſe of His,</hi> who have (through his Grace) followed him therein, <hi>according to their light,</hi> with faithfulneſs, to the <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Grounds,</hi> ſubſtance, and principal ends thereof, with leaſt mixture of their own, or other worldly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt intereſts, in the proſecution of it, and with trueſt deſires and endeavors for the ſuppreſſing or reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Common Enemies thereof, for the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, Protection and Advancement of thoſe that love and fear the Lord, and wait for his appearance; and in the mean time, for preſerving amongſt all ſuch the unity of faith in the bond of peace and love: And that if he ſhall yet ſee it good to compleat, or proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute any further the outward Victories of his people,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117881:8"/>againſt their outward Enemies and Oppreſſors in the world, he would glorifie the Power and Vertue of the Spirit of his Son in them, now at laſt, in giving them (through it) to overcome ſpiritually the Temptations of proſperity, and of the good things of the world, as hitherto it hath been, by their overcoming all Tryals and Sufferings in the evils thereof.</p>
            <p>Now laſtly, for the better and ſpeedier communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of what is herein required or deſired, I do hereby further Appoint the ſame to be Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at the Leaguer before <hi>Waterford,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 30. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>H: IRETON,</hi> Deputy General.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
